Guide to the Felix S. Cohen Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Felix S. Cohen papers
1916-1992
WA MSS S-1325
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
52.96
(155 boxes) + 7 broadside folders
The papers document Felix S. Cohen's professional career as a civil servant, private attorney, law professor, and author. From 1933-57, Cohen drafted legislation for the Department of Interior, most notably the Wheeler-Howard Indian Reorganization Act of 1934. In 1939 he headed the Indian Law Survey, which compiled all federal laws regarding Native Americans. He edited the summary of that survey, known as The Handbook of Federal Indian Law, which remains a milestone in the evolution of Indian law. Cohen continued to continued to work for Indian and minority interests in private practice in the late 1940s and early 1950s.
Other Storage Formats: Oversize, broadsides
Cohen, Felix S., 1907-1953
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of the collection was donated by Lucy M. Kramer Cohen in 1989 and 1991. "Statutory Compilation of the Indian Law Survey: A Compendium of Federal Laws and Treaties Relating to Indians" (Box 13) and Series VI (Boxes 97-99) were the gift of Arthur Lazarus of the law firm of Fried, Frank, Harris, Shriver & Kampelman.
Conditions Governing Access
Boxes 102-104, folders 1655-1693: Restricted until 2025. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 105, folders 1694-1695: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
FELIX S. COHEN (1907-1953)
Felix Solomon Cohen was a lawyer with special interest in natural resources, in statehood and economic development for American territories, in Indian affairs, and in immigration and minority problems. He was a professor of jurisprudence, a civil servant, and an author of numerous articles on law, ethics, and philosophy, on Native Americans and minorities, and on human and natural resources. From 1933 through 1947 he served in the Solicitor's Office of the Interior Department as an assistant solicitor, associate solicitor, and acting solicitor. He also served as chairman of the Office's Board of Appeals. Cohen drafted the Wheeler-Howard Act (later known as the Indian Reorganization Act) of 1934, and contributed to the department's handling of Indian and Eskimo aboriginal rights. In 1939 Cohen was named Chief of the Indian Law Survey, a joint project of the Lands Division of the Department of Justice and of the Department of Interior to compile all federal laws, treaties, etc., involving Native Americans. Cohen edited a summary of the 46-volume survey, which was published by the Interior Department as The Handbook of Federal Indian Law and remains a milestone in the evolution of Indian law. He received the Department's highest honor--the Distinguished Service Award--on retirement from government service in 1948.
Cohen re-entered private general law practice in January 1948, but continued to be interested in the legal affairs of Native Americans and immigrants, in human rights, and in natural resources. He eventually associated his Washington, D.C. office with the New York law firm of Riegelman, Strasser, Schwarz & Spiegelberg (which later became known in Washington as Fried, Frank, Harris, Shriver & Kampelman). Cohen handled several important pro bono Indian cases, particularly lawsuits which established Native Americans' rights to vote (in the last two states that had denied the franchise to them--New Mexico and Arizona), and to receive Social Security benefits in states that denied them such legal rights.
In 1946, Cohen had begun teaching legislative drafting and legal philosophy at Yale University's Law School, and jurisprudence at The City College of New York's Department of Philosophy. Cohen had also taught at the New School for School Research and the University of Newark Law School (later Rutgers Law School). In 1951 he published Readings in Jurisprudence and Legal Philosophy, the syllabus which he developed with his father, Morris R. Cohen, for both their jurisprudence courses (Morris Cohen at St. John's Law School and Felix Cohen at Rutgers and the New School for Social Research).
Felix S. Cohen was born in Manhattan, but grew up in Yonkers, New York. He attended The City College of New York, received an M.A. in philosophy from Harvard in 1927 and a Ph.D. from Harvard in 1929. In 1928 Cohen entered Columbia Law School, graduating in 1931. He married Lucy M. Kramer that year; they had two daughters. He died at his home in Washington, D.C., in October 1953. Additional biographical detail can be gleaned from other material in Series V of this collection. Box 91, folder 1469 contains a brief biography of Felix S. Cohen by his wife.
Scope and Contents
The Felix S. Cohen Papers document his legal, academic, and scholarly career. The collection spans the period 1916-92, but the bulk of the material covers Cohen's activities in the 1930s and 1940s.
The papers are arranged in five series. Series I, Legal Career, contains material from Felix Cohen's years as a legislative draftsman and solicitor for the Interior Department and as a private attorney. Series II, Teaching Career, documents Cohen's work as professor of jurisprudence and legislative drafting at Yale and City College of New York. Series III, Writing Projects, contains reviews, articles, addresses, books, and pamphlets by Cohen, as well as notes and background material. Series IV, Collegial - Institutional Affiliations, documents his relationship with the Institute of Living Law and other professional and charitable organizations. Series V, Personal Papers, contains material by, about, and collected by Felix S. Cohen and his wife, Lucy M. Kramer Cohen; his father, Morris R. Cohen; and Leonora C. and Harry N. Rosenfield, Felix Cohen's sister and her husband. Series VI, Arthur Lazarus Addition, contains Cohen's files on Indian constitutions.
Series I, Legal Career (Boxes 1-57) consists of released office files from Cohen's years with the Solicitor's Office of the Department of the Interior (1933-47) and from his private practice (1948-53). This series preserves the folder level content of Cohen's files as they were received by the Beinecke Library. Cohen's folder titles have been retained but the order of the files has been changed to provide better subject access to the materials that dominated Cohen's professional life. Four topical subseries contain Cohen's personal working files released by Interior, some of which were also used by Cohen in private practice. These are Indian Affairs, Indian Law Survey, Alaska: Natural Resources and Native Affairs, and Territories. Material that does not fit into these subject groupings is gathered with administrative files from the Interior Department in Solicitor's Office Records. Files created by Cohen after 1948 are arranged under Private Practice Office Records.
Indian Affairs consists of Interior files documenting the implementation of the Indian Reorganization Act of 1934 (IRA, known originally as the Wheeler-Howard Act) and routine legal work concerning the department's Indian policies. The files consist of internal memoranda; correspondence with outside experts, other government agencies, legislators, and private interest groups; drafts of reports and legal opinions; printed bills and drafts; and printed material by government agencies and private institutions. The files also contain articles written by Cohen, with supporting documentation, connected with his work for the department.
The first section of Indian Affairs (Box 1) contains articles by Cohen on Indian land rights. The next group of files (Boxes 2-4) revolves around the document "The New Trail," a report on how the IRA would affect Indian self-government and federal administration. File titles such as "Law and Order..." and "Indian citizenship" indicate issues examined by the Solicitor's Office. Box 2, folders 17-22 document a series of tribal council meetings set up by the Interior Department to discuss the IRA with the Five Civilized Tribes of Oklahoma, the Pueblo Indians, the Plains Indians, and the Indians of southern Arizona. There are several files relating to new regulations for the Indian Service and correspondence with Indian rights groups, such as the Association on American Indian Affairs, Inc.
Boxes 5-9 consist of internal documents reflecting routine Indian affairs of the Interior Department. Memoranda by the Solicitor's Office to other Interior offices, in particular the Office of the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, give advice on legal questions. Much of this material is related to the creation of Indian constitutions authorized under the IRA. This section contains correspondence among Cohen, Indian Service field workers, and tribal leaders and members regarding IRA and Indian constitutions. Drafts of model charters and constitutions can be found in Box 6 and documents outlining their implementation in Boxes 8-9. A key document on the IRA is a Solicitor's Opinion, a formal explanation of the legal ramifications of the IRA's empowerment of Indian tribes. The collection contains two drafts of the document, which is identified in the Cohen bibliography as "The Powers of an Indian Tribe" (Box 8, folders 111-12). [Felix S. Cohen, Ida K. Johnson, and Lucy M. Kramer Cohen, "Bibliography of Felix S. Cohen," Rutgers Law Review. IX (Winter 1954), no. 2:351-53. See Box 91, folder 1469.]
The rest of the subseries Indian Affairs relates to a variety of Indian issues handled by Cohen while working for Interior, such as rehabilitation, relief, and resettlement programs. A group of files labeled "Indian Affairs Record - 1933-37" contains material Cohen used to prepare a report for Solicitor Margold on the state of Indian Affairs post-IRA (Box 10, folders 138-41). The files consist of correspondence with John Collier (Commissioner of Indian Affairs), internal memoranda, and an issue of Indians at Work.
Indian Law Survey (Boxes 11-17) documents a 1939-40 joint project by the Departments of Interior and Justice. Felix S. Cohen was named chief of the project and work was carried out at Justice until December 1939. The project was completed by the Interior Department. The goal was to create a file of federal legislation and treaties concerning Native Americans. This file was internally published by Interior in 1940 in a 46 volume set entitled the "Statutory Compilation of the Indian Law Survey: A Compendium of Federal Laws and Treaties Relating to Indians." Cohen's private copy became the property of his law firm and was donated to the collection by one of his colleagues. The second result of the project was a guide to this "Compilation," which was first published by the Government Printing office in 1940 as the Handbook of Federal Indian Law. This initial edition of the Handbook was in two volumes: the text in one volume and reference tables and index in a second volume. The second printing in 1941 and 1942 was in one volume.
The first two sections of Indian Law Survey, Reports and Memoranda and Correspondence, document the operation of the survey. Through a series of reports to administrators, including the assistant attorney general, Cohen notes the progress of the "Compilation" files, the status of the indexing, and the legal areas covered (Box 11, folders 156-67). Internal memoranda and other reports document decisions on the scope and content of the "Compilation" (Box 12, folders 168-70). Memoranda and Correspondence (Boxes 12-13, folders 172-91) consists of internal communication among the Indian Survey staff regarding equipment, supplies, and personnel. The third section is the "Compilation" in 1940 printed form.
The fourth section of Indian Law Survey (Boxes 14-16) consists of drafts and page proofs of the first edition of the Handbook of Federal Indian Law, along with information on the printing and distribution of the work. The most complete draft is followed by drafts of individual chapters. The draft and comments in Box 14, folders 240-47 document the conflict between the Survey staff and the Justice Department which caused the termination of the joint project and its assumption by the Interior Department. Interspersed with the text are criticisms of the Handbook by members of the Justice Department and the analysis by an outside expert, William A. Brophy. This controversy is also mentioned in communications with the Department of Justice, Box 13, folders 176-82. The final section of Indian Law Survey (Box 17) consists of background material used by the staff.
Series I continues with Alaska: Natural Resources and Native Affairs (Boxes 18-30), which documents the Interior Department's Alaskan policies of the 1940s. Cohen originally created these files when working for the department, but many contain material dating from his private practice. Files consist of internal reports and memoranda, and correspondence with Alaskan Indian attorneys, Interior's field agents, Indian rights groups, and groups interested in resettling refugees to Alaska. Cohen's files focus on the development and settlement of Alaska and Native Alaskan land and on fishing rights.
Box 18 contains drafts of a 1941 act allowing groups to incorporate for the purpose of settling Alaska. The two major reports used by Interior are "The Problem of Alaskan Development" and "New Horizons for Alaska: A Survey of Economic Resources and Conditions for Future Development of the Territory" (Box 18, folders 310-15). Along with Interior memoranda and reports, there is correspondence and printed material from the Freeland League and the Conference on Jewish Relations, two organizations interested in Alaska as a home for Europeans fleeing Hitlerism.
Cohen's files (Boxes 19-20) also address the issue of native fishing rights versus commercial fishing companies. The conflict centered on the claims by the villages Kake, Hydabury, and Klawock to fishing sites and land inhabited by both settlers and native peoples. Files contain reports on Congressional hearings, claims filed by the Interior Department, a report to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs on the 1944 hearings (Box 19, folder 335), press releases, and newspaper articles. This material traces the conflict between the Indians supported by Interior on the one part and the federal government and Alaskan citizens on the other. Folder 1038 contains the "Alaska-Wide Anti-Indian Reservation Edition," a special issue of the Ketchikan Alaska Chronicle. Throughout this section there is correspondence to and from William A. Brophy (Commissioner of Indian Affairs), William L. Paul, Jr. (Indian attorney in Juneau), George Folta (counsel at large in Juneau for Interior), and Theodore H. Haas (law division, office of Indian Affairs).
Boxes 21-22 focus on the settlements between the Alaskan natives and the commercial fishing industry. There are drafts of the new fishing regulations of 1946, agreements (Box 21, folder 352), internal reports on the conservation and usage of Alaskan fisheries (Box 21, folders 353-58), and statements by the Interior Department to members of Congress explaining "the possessory rights of Alaskan natives," which served as Interior's main argument for Indian ownership of vast lands and fishing sites (Boxes 21-22, folders 361-63, 368-69). Included are copies of Alaskan legislation on salmon trapsites (Box 22, folders 370-71) and decisions on the claims. Box 22, folders 372-73 contain a good summary of the Hydaburg case.
Boxes 23 consists of general Alaskan business for 1940-47. These files are mostly memoranda by Cohen, Solicitor Margold, and Haas, stating their opinions on the Alaskan fisheries cases. Internal documents note the forming of fisherman associations in Alaska, the emergence of the Alaskan Native Brotherhood and Sisterhood as bargaining units for Indians in the salmon canneries, and absentee ownership of fish traps.
Box 24 contains files on Senate bill 3577, the Alaskan settlement and development bill of 1939-41. There are notes and correspondence regarding the bills and various drafts, along with the published text of the Congressional hearings. Senate Joint Resolution 162, seeking to abolish Alaskan Indian Reservations, and Interior's response, can be found in Box 24, folders 399-402). The remainder of Box 24 - Box 25 consists of files of correspondence and drafts of Cohen's articles on Alaskan legislation and Indian rights.
Near the end of the subseries Alaska: Natural Resources and Native Affairs is a section Cohen labeled "Current Alaska Material" (Boxes 26-30). It seems to be a collection of files he created in the 1940s while working at Interior and later used in his private practice. The files document the Tongass timber case, which addressed the issue of whether the Department of Agriculture could sell timber from land belonging to Indians (Box 26-27, folders 419-22, 436). The next case involves the Karluk village's offshore fishing rights. The law firm of Curry, [Henry] Cohen & Bingham (CC&B) represented the Indians while Felix S. Cohen represented the Association on American Indian Affairs. Along with legal papers, the files contain correspondence with Don C. Foster, superintendent with the Alaskan Native Service in Juneau, and maps of the waters surrounding Kodiak Island annotated to show the location of fishing rights. Several other cases handled by Cohen after 1948 in private practice are represented in Boxes 27-28. The last few files focus on the attempt in the late 1940s to extinguish Alaskan native land rights. There is correspondence with William Paul, Don Foster, James E. Curry, and Oliver LaFarge, the president of the Association on American Indian Affairs.
The last files in Alaska: Natural Resources and Native Affairs (Boxes 29-30) concern another case of possessory-aboriginal rights, that of the Tlingit and Haida Indians. William Paul is involved and the files have much background material supplied by Paul and copies of Interior documents spelling out possessory rights. There is correspondence with Rita Singer, a lawyer working with Cohen.
The fourth subseries of Series I, Territories (Boxes 30-36), contains Cohen's Interior files consisting primarily of draft reports and memoranda, press releases, and other documents by the department. The problems Cohen worked on include immigration of World War II refugees to United States territories, such as the Virgin Islands, establishing the status of the territory of Guam, and the human and natural resources of Puerto Rico. In particular, Cohen defended Governor Rexford Guy Tugwell in the case of Suarez-Martinez v. Tugwell, an agricultural company case involving the sugar industry. Cohen created legal plans for semi-governmental, semi-private corporations and authorities for the development of agriculture, industry, water, and other resources in Puerto Rico (Boxes 31-33). There are several typescript articles by Cohen on Puerto Rico, which may relate to some of his published pieces (Box 32, folder 501).
The fifth subseries of Series I, Solicitor's Office Records (Boxes 37-50), contains Cohen's work on issues not included in the preceding subseries and the administrative paperwork of the Solicitor's Office. The folder titles in Boxes 37-42 reflect the issues with which Cohen was involved, such as immigrants, atomic energy, and public lands and natural resources. The last file in this group (Box 42, folders 636-39) contains Cohen's paperwork just prior to his departure from the Interior Department. It includes a 16-page memorandum by Cohen to the solicitor entitled "Effect of Alaskan Cession Treaty on Native Possessory Rights," dated December 12, 1947.
Boxes 43-47 consist of the Solicitor's Office annual reports, correspondence, memoranda, opinions, and departmental press releases. This material is organized chronologically and presents an overview of the Solicitor's Office activities in the 1940s. Succeeding files contain information on the structure of the Solicitor's Office, its place in the Interior Department, and a record of its interaction with other departmental agencies (Boxes 47-48, folders 706-27). The last section of Solicitor's Office Records concerns employment issues and includes several files on Cohen's employment by the Interior Department (Boxes 49-50, folders 740-45).
Private Practice Office Records (Boxes 50-57) documents Cohen's legal practice beginning in January 1948 in Washington, D.C. Cohen worked closely with other Indian attorneys, in particular the law firm of CC&B. To keep current on Indian affairs, this group produced a "Daily Publications Digest" (Box 50, folders 746-49). The "Digest" summarizes articles in Alaskan and New Mexico newspapers, the Congressional Record, and the Federal Register. The majority of the notes are on Alaskan issues. Although Cohen himself never accepted any Indian Claims the "Digest" includes two lists of Commission contracts approved by the Indian Office, dated February 7 and May 13, 1948. The "Digest" seems to have been circulated to Felix S. Cohen, as well as the attorneys of CC&B: Frances Lopinsky, James Curry, Henry Cohen, and Jonathan Bingham.
Most files are identified by the names of the clients, who include several institutions. His work for the American Jewish Committee and the New York Association for New Americans (NYANA) concerned immigrants. For NYANA Cohen prepared a series of memoranda in response to Congressional immigration bills (Box 52-53, folders 797-808). For the Consultative Council of Jewish Organizations, he wrote a memorandum on the prevention of discrimination and protection of minorities for submission to the United Nations Commission on Human Rights (Boxes 50-51, folders 761-71). The files for the Institute of Ethnic Affairs show Cohen as legal adviser, member, and director. Included are publications by and about the institute and copies of confidential memoranda by John Collier in 1946 documenting the United States delegation to the United Nations and discussion of international trusteeships.
Many of the files in Private Practice Office Records relate to Indian affairs. The folder on Elizabeth Chief concerns action against her as a Navajo social worker, but the background material, including photographs, reveal health conditions among Navajo children. The files labeled Frances Lopinsky Horn, Marks & Marks, William Paul, Rita Singer, Henry Weihofen, Ernest L. Wilkinson, and C. M. Wright are all correspondence with lawyers with whom Cohen worked on Indian cases. These files document Cohen's cases, what his thoughts were, and with whom he was working. Cohen's travel records (Box 53, folders 821-26) include correspondence and itineraries of trips to the southwest in 1948, 1949, and 1950. These business trips were opportunities to meet with clients such as the Jicarilla Apache, New Mexican Indians (voting case), All-Pueblo Council, Hualapai, Wisconsin Oneidas, Omaha Tribal Council, Pine Ridge Oglala Sioux Tribal Council, and the Blackfeet Tribal Council.
Boxes 53-57 contain Cohen's time records. Some documents organize the data by lawyer, some by client, and some give monthly totals. Time sheets (Boxes 53-56, folders 827-96) are a daily record of the time spent for various clients and what he did. For 1949-51 these records include monthly summations which list the client, the amount of work, and when it took place. Similar monthly totals for 1948 can be found in Box 57, folder 907. Daily notes (Box 57, folders 897-904) are on 3" x 5" slips of paper contain notes from Felix S. Cohen's law office and CC&B law firm telling what various lawyer did. Initials are often used and stand for the following lawyers: FSC - Felix S. Cohen; FL - Frances Lopinsky; JEC - James E. Curry; and RS - Rita Singer. Monthly totals for each lawyer, organized by client, can be found for 1948-52 (Box 57, folders 907-09 and folders 1648-49).